<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">BMJ Technology</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://technology.bmj.com/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://technology.bmj.com" />
<updated>2015-05-20T16:03:28+01:00</updated>
<id>http://technology.bmj.com/</id>
<author>
  <name>BMJTech</name>
  <uri>http://technology.bmj.com/</uri>
  <email>support@bmj.com</email>
</author>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[BMJ switch to Google Apps]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://technology.bmj.com/switch-to-google/" />
  <id>http://technology.bmj.com/switch-to-google</id>
  <published>2014-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>BMJTech</name>
    <uri>http://technology.bmj.com</uri>
    <email>support@bmj.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;We left the environment of shared drives, Microsoft Office 2007 and Lotus Notes where ‘file in use’ was a common greeting in the morning followed by “Your mail file has exceeded the size threshold. You should delete messages and compact your mail file” .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, these dated systems are a thing of the past and we’re now working in an environment fit for our time, on an infrastructure that supports us rather than confronts us. We are experiencing freedoms that were previously unimaginable: using devices of our choosing, in locations of our choosing and having video meetings on demand without reserving expensive equipment in unavailable meeting rooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back now, I can see clearly how bad things were and how I am now so much more productive, more creative and more sociable — working with friends and colleagues collaboratively all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get the full story on &lt;a href=&quot;googleforwork.blogspot.co.uk/2014/10/bmj-revamps-office-culture-with-shift.html&quot;&gt;our digital transformation here&lt;/a&gt; and also see related tweets at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?screen_name=gonegoogle&quot;&gt;#gonegoogle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://technology.bmj.com/switch-to-google/&quot;&gt;BMJ switch to Google Apps&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by BMJTech at &lt;a href=&quot;http://technology.bmj.com&quot;&gt;BMJ Technology&lt;/a&gt; on October 14, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[BMJ Learning A/B Testing]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://technology.bmj.com/learning-AB/" />
  <id>http://technology.bmj.com/learning-AB</id>
  <published>2014-09-26T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-09-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Pedro Lopez</name>
    <uri>http://technology.bmj.com</uri>
    <email>plopez@bmj.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h2 id=&quot;reasons&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reasons&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the principle of Lean Startup is to measure how customers respond, and we believe little changes can lead to big improvements.  Hence the team has decided to use Google Content Experiments to gather data related to the customer response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;steps&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steps&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first AB test implemented on &lt;a href=&quot;http://learning.bmj.com&quot;&gt;BMJ Learning&lt;/a&gt; was a trivial test to find out whether minor changes to our homepage would attract more registrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hypothesis&quot;&gt;Hypothesis:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homepage with different colour button will have a higher conversion rate than a homepage page with the same blue colour button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;success-metric&quot;&gt;Success Metric:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversion rate as measured by the number of button click over the number of visits to each page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;volume-and-statistical-significance&quot;&gt;Volume and Statistical Significance:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test run for 38 days and accumulated 21,540 experiment sessions to the three pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;test-group-and-split&quot;&gt;Test Group and Split:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We set Google Content Experiments to distribute traffic evenly across the three variants of the homepage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;randomization&quot;&gt;Randomization:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Content Experiments was used to run the test and make sure that the traffic driven to these pages was randomly distributed between the three test pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.bmj.com/technology/files/2014/09/abtesting12.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://blogs.bmj.com/technology/files/2014/09/abtesting12-300x95.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;abtesting1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;winner&quot;&gt;Winner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winner of first AB test was the second version with a conversion rate of 4.55% compare to the original and the third version. This shows that the more obvious registration button will attract more attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second AB test implemented on BMJ Learning was a test to find out if users prefer the registration journey on a single page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hypothesis-1&quot;&gt;Hypothesis:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One page registration journey will have a higher conversion rate compare to multiple pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;success-metric-1&quot;&gt;Success Metric:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversion rate as measured by the number of users that completed the registration journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;volume-and-statistical-significance-1&quot;&gt;Volume and Statistical Significance:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Test run for 15 days and accumulated 20,059 experiment sessions to the two pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;test-group-and-split-1&quot;&gt;Test Group and Split:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We set Google Content Experiments to distribute traffic evenly across the two variants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;randomization-1&quot;&gt;Randomization:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Content Experiments was used to run the test and make sure that the traffic driven to these pages was randomly distributed between the two test pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.bmj.com/technology/files/2014/09/abtesting2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://blogs.bmj.com/technology/files/2014/09/abtesting2-300x113.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;abtesting2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;winner-1&quot;&gt;Winner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winner of second AB test was the second version with a conversion rate of 6.34% compare to the original that only has 1.96%. This shows that a simple sign-up form attracts significantly more users than a more complex version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lessons-learned&quot;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When there is no substantial data to back up certain changes and there isn’t enough market research to support a new feature, AB testing is a great way to find out the best solution for the customers instead of just relying on gut feelings or a figure plucked from the air.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://technology.bmj.com/learning-AB/&quot;&gt;BMJ Learning A/B Testing&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by BMJTech at &lt;a href=&quot;http://technology.bmj.com&quot;&gt;BMJ Technology&lt;/a&gt; on September 26, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[BMJ JobReviews]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://technology.bmj.com/bmj-jobreviews/" />
  <id>http://technology.bmj.com/bmj-jobreviews</id>
  <published>2014-09-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-09-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Pedro Lopez</name>
    <uri>http://technology.bmj.com</uri>
    <email>plopez@bmj.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jobreviews.bmj.com/&quot;&gt;Job Reviews&lt;/a&gt; is a new BMJ product that will let doctors create reviews of medical jobs, posts, and rotations. It is designed as a mobile first responsive website and it is part of the BMJ Careers family of products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article I will describe the reasons behind this project, how we implemented it and what is next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;architecture&quot;&gt;Architecture&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Job Reviews is a combination of two different modules (see Figure 1). As a result we have a small SOA (Service Oriented Architecture):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Back-end&lt;/strong&gt;: exposes the data and functionality as an API following the HAL specification [HALSpec].&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Front-end&lt;/strong&gt;: user interface that communicates with the back-end through its API and renders the information in a responsive and user friendly way.
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.bmj.com/technology/files/2014/09/Tech-Blog-Job-Reviews.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://blogs.bmj.com/technology/files/2014/09/Tech-Blog-Job-Reviews.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tech Blog - Job Reviews&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 1. Overview of the Architecture of Job Reviews&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many new technologies involved in both modules. Some of them were never used before at the BMJ, including the latest version of Node.js, 0.11.x at the current date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the most relevant ones:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Back-end&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Node.js [Node]: platform built on Chrome’s JavaScript runtime for easily building fast, scalable network applications. Node.js uses an event-driven, non-blocking I/O model that makes it lightweight and efficient, perfect for data-intensive real-time applications that run across distributed devices.&lt;/p&gt;

        &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;*   Co [Co]: Generator based flow-control goodness for Node.js and the browser, using thunks or promises, letting you write non-blocking code in a nice-ish way. *   Koa [Koa]: Koa is a new web framework designed by the team behind Express, which aims to be a smaller, more expressive, and more robust foundation for web applications and APIs. Through leveraging generators Koa allows you to ditch callbacks and greatly increase error-handling.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Front-end&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;AngularJS [Angular]: AngularJS is an open-source web application framework, maintained by Google and community, that assists with creating single-page applications, one-page web applications that only require HTML, CSS, and JavaScript on the client side.
We also used Gulp [Gulp] for building and Mocha[Mocha] and Protractor [Protractor] for testing the back-end and front-end respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We created a Continuous Delivery [CD] pipeline that we used as part of our continuous integration and release strategies. This let us validate our code very often and put new features into production automatically very easily. Given that we built this product following a BDD/TDD approach, this was fundamental in order to achieve our quality goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, we made use of Vagrant [Vagrant] to box up everything in a reusable Linux-based container.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;development-process&quot;&gt;Development process&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Job Reviews was built up in our Co-Lab laboratory were a study was conducted in order to validate the need for the tool and the interest of the medical community. It was decided to tackle this project as a mobile first website in order to make the most of the new trends in usability and UX (User Experience).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once this initial work was done, the project was handed to a Scrum team in the Technology department that followed an agile iterative approach to build the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process began with an Impact Mapping [IMap] session to make sure everybody was on the same page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Impact mapping is a strategic planning technique that prevents organisations from getting lost while building products and delivering projects, by clearly communicating assumptions, helping teams align their activities with overall business objectives and make better roadmap decisions.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the TDD principle “write the tests first” a high quality product was built and released to production through a Continuous Delivery pipeline created in a Jenkins CI (Continuous Integration) server.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BDD was used in the front-end module in order to collaborate with the product owner and other domain experts. As a result we all got a shared understanding of the domain model while creating a collection of feature descriptions to be used as both a development guide and as a suite of automated tests scripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scrum team coordinated with the Operations team to set up the load-balanced servers and the deployment scripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used the GitFlow convention as our branching model [GitFlow].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;mvp&quot;&gt;MVP&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a few pre-releases, we finally released the first MVP (Minimum Viable Product) in beta [JR]  (see Figure 2), which is accessible from the BMJ Careers site [Careers].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://blogs.bmj.com/technology/files/2014/09/mvp.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;mvp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 2. Evolution of the Job Reviews UI&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This first version includes the following features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Search for Hospitals and LETBs: as the user types in the name of a hospital or LETB he will receive suggestions. If the input is not descriptive enough to narrow down the results to less than 10 items, the user will be given a “Show more” option to get to a results page in order to browse all the matching results.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inspect hospital details: once the user gets to the relevant hospital details page, information of that hospital will be displayed, such as address and contact details when available, and previous reviews and statistics.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Submit a review: on the hospital details page, the user will be able to submit his own review. It will be posted anonymously. The user will need to verify his identity via a Facebook account or an email address.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step in the roadmap is to let the users decide the future of this product. It will be available as a beta for a period of time, during which we will gather user feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some improvements we already have in mind include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Additional search criteria such as by location, by postcode or by score.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Additional sign up mechanisms including Twitter or Google+.
So the very next thing is spread the word and get as much feedback as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;http://stateless.co/hal_specification.html&quot;&gt;HALSpec&lt;/a&gt;] HAL Specification&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;http://nodejs.org/&quot;&gt;Node&lt;/a&gt;] Node.js official site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/visionmedia/co&quot;&gt;Co&lt;/a&gt;] Co repository in GitHub&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;http://koajs.com/&quot;&gt;Koa&lt;/a&gt;] Koa official site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;https://angularjs.org/&quot;&gt;Angular&lt;/a&gt;] AngularJS official site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;http://gulpjs.com/&quot;&gt;Gulp&lt;/a&gt;] Gulp official site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;http://visionmedia.github.io/mocha/&quot;&gt;Mocha&lt;/a&gt;] Mocha official site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;http://angular.github.io/protractor/#/&quot;&gt;Protractor&lt;/a&gt;] Protractor official site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;http://continuousdelivery.com/&quot;&gt;CD&lt;/a&gt;] Blog about Continuos Delivery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vagrantup.com/&quot;&gt;Vagrant&lt;/a&gt;] Vagrant official site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.impactmapping.org/&quot;&gt;IMap&lt;/a&gt;] Impact Mapping official site&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;http://nvie.com/posts/a-successful-git-branching-model/&quot;&gt;GitFlow&lt;/a&gt;] Blog post about GitFlow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;http://jobreviews.bmj.com/&quot;&gt;JR&lt;/a&gt;] BMJ Careers - Job Reviews&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[&lt;a href=&quot;http://careers.bmj.com/&quot;&gt;Careers&lt;/a&gt;] BMJ Careers site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://technology.bmj.com/bmj-jobreviews/&quot;&gt;BMJ JobReviews&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by BMJTech at &lt;a href=&quot;http://technology.bmj.com&quot;&gt;BMJ Technology&lt;/a&gt; on September 18, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Every sprint is sacred]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://technology.bmj.com/every-sprint-scared/" />
  <id>http://technology.bmj.com/every-sprint-scared</id>
  <published>2014-09-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-09-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://technology.bmj.com</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;“Owning” an online product as it declutters, rebrands, replatforms, and “responds” to desktop, tablet, and smartphone devices can be a scary business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was asked to share these tips, based on my experience of &lt;a href=&quot;http://thebmj.com&quot; title=&quot;The BMJ&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The BMJ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; responsive design and Drupal 7 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drupal.org/node/2323999&quot; title=&quot;Drupal case study&quot;&gt;migration project&lt;/a&gt;, to help fellow product owners as they grapple with Agile, scrums, sprints, backlog grooming, stand-ups, and “show and tells.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scrum teams change. Get over it&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The last time I was in a scrum was between 1977 and 1982, and for most of those five years I was in the second row with my arm round David Severn and my face wedged against Ian Farrell’s backside. We got to know each other very well.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The BMJ_ scrum team changed more regularly than my school rugby team. Don’t let this unsettle you. Some developers in BMJ’s Technology team were pulled on to different projects, and contractors joined as the project progressed.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;It’s not your call as product owner who is in the team. They will learn from each other (and from you), and the more people who get to know your product in the technology team, the better. Single points of failure are not good. This is probably why the team  at BMJ rotated the role of scrum master, which worked really well.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beware sprint saboteurs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Every two weeks we met to score and prioritise tasks and bugs in the backlog, and a follow up sprint planning meeting gave us a list of scored stories to keep everybody busy for the next fortnight. You’ll probably face pressure from business colleagues and others to rejig priorities and slot in new tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Hold your nerve (even if they look like they’re going to cry. Or shout at you. Or both). You’re the product owner with the best sense of what needs doing. Every sprint is sacred (to adapt a line from Monty Python), and if you add something, it will almost certainly mean another task won’t get done.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Know your front end from your back end&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The panto horse analogy really does apply here. Your scrum team will probably consist of front end and back end developers. You don’t want your back end twiddling its thumbs while the front end is struggling to keep up with all the design challenges you’ve given it to do. But don’t get too hung up about this. The important thing that the team as a whole is working on top priority tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No showing and yelling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;At the end of code release there is a chance to showcase what the team has achieved. If you’re smart you’ll invite lots of people across the business to see this.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Think of this “show and tell” as a slot at the Edinburgh Fringe, so do the equivalent of handing out flyers in the Royal Mile - don’t just invite your mates, who will give an you an easy ride. When your audience arrives, imagine they have paid for a ticket, so try to make it entertaining. Be respectful, even if they’re asking awkward questions. Their feedback will help you plan future sprints.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Lead the session by setting the scene and explaining what the sprint achieved. But don’t hog the limelight. Hand over to scrum team colleagues to explain stuff in more detail. This applies especially to anything with an acronym. And BDD. And something called Jenkins.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Finally, don’t spend too long showcasing a back end admin interface that will only be used by a handful of editors, however proud the team are of it. Try to focus on things that will interest your audience the most.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t give up the day job&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;If you’re a product owner you’re probably also a line manager. Your team will end up working on the product after it goes live, so their feedback is gold dust. Involve them at every opportunity, particularly with testing, and remember that they are doing a fantastic job keeping the current product updated while the new one gets developed. If, like me, your Myers Briggs is ENFP, having a ISTJ co-pilot (or something similar), is essential. Otherwise you’re stuffed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be a jack of all trades&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;At times you will look back nostalgically at the days when you had a dedicated project manager and a budget for user testing. (This involved sitting behind a screen in St Albans, watching a bunch of doctors confuse you with The &lt;em&gt;Lancet&lt;/em&gt; and moan about why the contents aren’t on a blue front cover anymore).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Those days are long gone. User testing now involves sharing the pre-live site after every release with editorial board members, colleagues, friends, foes, and random readers you are allowed to email without upsetting the data protection applecart. Make sure you log their feedback (it’s priceless) and use it to inform future sprints.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Life can be tough without a project manager. It’s down to you to arrange pizza and beer on the night you do your “first public release”  but it can mean you get closer to the actual development team, which is a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Double-desk David&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;There really is no substitute for sitting with the scrum team. You will accomplish a lot more in each sprint, and you will learn a lot in the process. The team will want you to clarify tasks, look at designs, and warn you about any show-stoppers. I tended to stay after the daily 10 am stand-up meeting whenever possible. BMJ’s Technology department had better coffee, comfier sofas, and home baking. It also has more chocolate than anywhere else at BMJ Towers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A bug’s life&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;You will launch with bugs. Don’t believe anyone who tells you otherwise. So make sure you get some “post-launch” sprints approved to fix them. These sprints can also include any features that don’t constitute “minimum viable product.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Minimum viable product&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This term stinks. It sounds like you’re consigning your cherished newborn digital product to the online equivalent of a special care baby unit. But applying this definition does help you prioritise. Do you really need the ability to filter online article responses according to the writer’s horoscope? If you do, can it wait until after you’re live?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Take a break&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the old days a project usually had a launch date, so you tended to put your life on hold and book a long overdue two week holiday within days of it going live as all the bugs appeared. 
   So did everybody else. But Agile projects aren’t subject to the same constraints, so don’t feel guilty if you abandon the scrum team for a week or so midway through the project. It’s important that they do the same thing too, so you all stay refreshed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;david-payne-is-digital-editor-thebmjcom&quot;&gt;David Payne is digital editor, thebmj.com&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The BMJ&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (formerly the British Medical Journal) is an international peer reviewed medical journal dating back to 1840. Online since 1995, thebmj.com is updated daily with_ The BMJ’s_ latest original research, education, news, and comment articles, as well as podcasts, videos, and blogs. &lt;em&gt;The BMJ’s&lt;/em&gt; team is based mainly in London, although we also have editors elsewhere in Europe, in the US, and in India.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://technology.bmj.com/every-sprint-scared/&quot;&gt;Every sprint is sacred&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by BMJTech at &lt;a href=&quot;http://technology.bmj.com&quot;&gt;BMJ Technology&lt;/a&gt; on September 05, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>
